I just watched the curse of creativity
by Jordan Peterson and I found it
brilliant I agreed with a lot of the
stuff but there's a lot of stuff that I
think he conflates himself that just
because is how things are done in
capitalism doesn't mean it's the only
way
and yet as an individual trying to do
this who's creative and trying to bring
something out in the world this spoke to
me very strongly because these are the
thoughts like I know how did that this
is how you be successful at creativity
and yet I'm not capable of it and so
I've had to think myself around those
things which solve it for everybody and
so I want to talk about the whole video
I also got pointed out yesterday and it
resonated that I I think we all like I
want to say tear someone down but that's
not right like if someone says something
and there's a piece I don't agree with
that's the one I want to do the video
response up right is the piece I don't
agree with rockingest sit there and
Herald their brilliance for the 90% it's
the piece that sticks that's like no
don't agree so I'm trying to do a more
balanced video talks about the curse of
creativity he says you have to be pretty
smart to be creative I think you have a
certain type of intelligence to be
creative all the different types of
intelligence you can be creative in that
you have to have divergent thinking
capabilities that you have to think of
novelty and something new that's the
definition of creativity so yes
absolutely he talks about you have to be
fast out in front I don't think that's
being creative that's being successful
at being creative for instance there's a
lot of innovation that happens that
multiple people will come up with at the
same time with Darwin and Wallace or
Tesla and Edison if you're in that field
you absolutely have to be first to
market if you're gonna be successful at
it but like Tesla's now being known for
his genius that was in my opinion more
of a genius than Edison but Edison was a
better business person and so
that doesn't mean we got the best
product it means that we thought the
best of us at this and that's kind of
what Jordan Peterson's talking about is
you need to be all of it for your idea
to be successful and I don't think you
would necessarily disagree that that's
somewhat of a broken system even if he
doesn't know the solution I kind of know
the solution he talks about that you if
you're a creative person you're looking
for aesthetic experiences and novelty
that you do creative endeavors you read
fiction you enjoy music that's different
as someone who has realized I'm very
creative
I'm very innovative in my thinking and
yet the only one of those that applies
is reading fiction to me that is the
caricature of somebody who's creative of
an artist that doesn't mean that
everybody is creativity falls in that
box and I think he would I don't think
he would escape that but that that is
heavily correlated with being creative
absolutely I don't understand why people
are you cease novelty and then it sparks
novelty I can see my mundane and spark
novelty I can see a more formal or more
function over form that's fine we need
creativity in all endeavors we need
different people to be he's he kind of
says like saying everyone's creative his
like saying everyone's an introvert yes
and you are saying that like you're
saying that if you're creative you have
these specific characteristics know
they're correlated they're not actually
needed to be creative you can be
creative without those high-risk
high-reward strategy
absolutely and yet as somebody who's
very risk-averse that means my idea is
not going to get out there luckily I've
figured out how to do it in a way that
isn't risky that isn't financially risky
it isn't and my life yeah I got brain
tumors worked out to the point where
unable to what he talks it later which I
will I'll get into and that's the
high-risk high-reward strategy if you're
monetizing the creativity right to
actually monetize it to actually make a
living at it and that's the piece I
think we need to solve together so that
we can unleash the creativity of
humanity on humanity's problems he talks
about if you build a better Mouse
we somehow think the world will beat a
path to your door and of course that's
not true because you have to be able to
do all of these things I agree which is
why it's broken which is why the market
for getting ight the best ideas out
there is it the best instrument because
it gets the best of the ideas that can
do all of these things not the best idea
not the best mousetrap the best
mousetrap that has the marketing the
sales the customer support someone who's
able capable of building an organization
able to communicate the new idea of the
mousetrap which you know itself has to
be marketed and as somebody who is
working on the building the organization
from an internal standpoint and the
communication of the idea but it's not
great at either of those pieces but the
thing the mousetrap that I'm creating
solves all these problems for everyone
so it is amazing yes but there's just
that to be he's not talking about being
creative he's talking about the curse of
creativity because you can't want it
because you might not be able to
monetize it so I think he knows they're
different things he's not necessarily
separating them in this talk we need to
separate them we need to be able to get
the best ideas out there he talks about
how their family and friends
sorry head and alarm clocks just went
off um your family and friends have to
have money and believe in you and then
they're taking a big risk
he didn't say believe in you I put that
down because the truth is the more
innovative your idea is another
something here that I was like oh if
you're somebody who comes off as super
capable like bravado capable like I
could do everything and he's your phone
was gonna be more likely to believe in
you even them they can see you failed
and everything you tried you think it's
a success introverts and a lot of
autistic people and a lot have amazing
ideas they aren't very innovative that
they're not going to have that inner
confidence to get it out there even to
their family and friends as someone
who's been in that boat and realized oh
your family and friends aren't actually
the people um who can see the beauty and
the idea or they would have come up with
it like it's it's a different I don't
know like they had the same life
experience they came up with different
different ideas different things that
they
you're innovative but I don't know like
how my whatever we're not gonna get into
family dynamics
that's your capital that that is where
you go and then you have to give away a
piece of your idea what if instead we
gave it away to humanity and humanity
funded it right that is what we're
working on with the global tech
cooperative overwhelming probability is
that you will fail but a small
percentage of the creative people
succeed spectacularly that's a lucky
calls it a lottery so that means we're
leaving solutions up to a lottery and
what we need right now are rapid
effective solutions to deal with the
problems as fast as we call caused them
and look for the truth the actual actual
solution not what we can mark it as the
solution and those are very different
things and so he talks about this fruit
tree which I love because Kyle sees
talks about a fruit tree which I've
talked about a few of my videos of that
a fruit tree doesn't care what it's
doing with its apples it just produces
the apples and the rest of the world can
you make applesauce you make apple pie
he talks about it like it's just you're
gonna get sick if you don't produce and
I agree I agree so it's just about
producing and he also talks about find a
way to make money and then Purdue pursue
your creativity this is where I lucked
out and got brain tumors cuz I get to be
on disability and be home to do my to do
my endeavors and that piece of it we can
give everyone with something like UVI
something like we just make sure
everyone's food shelter clothing needs
are met and it less and less cost
together collectively without leaving it
up to the government which is why I
propose we can unleash creativity you
don't need to take the risk you don't
need to be the risk-taker you don't need
to be the market or your name to be the
salesperson all you need to do is do the
creativity piece and so that were that
were that were my comments that was my
comments on the curse of creativity
Jordan Peterson thank you for doing that
video I think it was it was amazing and
I got a lot out of it for like yeah I
get it I have to be able to mark in it I
feel the communicated he talks about
like it's such an innovative idea no
one's gonna know how to search it bridge
enjoy the choir
no one wants to dismantle capitalism of
the world where the co-operative we all
have together democracy and transparency
no one's searching that on Google zero
searches as its each and every month but
a better world is on its way please like
and subscribe I'll see you next time
something sparks my creativity and I
want to do video Pio